Finding Aid for George John Wallace papers, 1929-1985
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George John Wallace papers
1929-1985
Wallace, George John, 1906-
2009092 Aa 2
Ornithologist; professor of zoology at Michigan State University; correspondence, organizational files, collected materials on the use of pesticides, bird lists, and course materials.
10 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection came from Wallace’s grandson Charles McGrath (donor no. 10188 ) in April 2009.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
George John Wallace was born December 9, 1906 in Waterbury, Vermont. He graduated from the University of Michigan with degrees in zoology (A.B., 1932; M.A., 1933; Ph.D., 1936). His first professional position was as a biologist with the Vermont Fish and Game Service (1936-1937). He then went to Lenox, Massachusetts as director of the Pleasant Valley Sanctuary (1937-1942). In 1942, he came to Michigan State College (now University) as instructor in zoology. He was made full professor in 1954.
A specialist in ornithology, Wallace was an active member of many professional organizations, including the American Ornithologists' Union, the Wilson Ornithological Society, the Michigan Audubon Society, and Michigan Bird Banders. For several years in the 1940s and 50s, Wallace was editor of Jack Pine Warbler, the newsletter of the Michigan Audubon Society. A respected teacher of zoology and ornithology, Wallace was the author of numerous articles and An Introduction to Ornithology considered by many to be the standard textbook in the field of ornithology. In 1979, he published his autobiography entitled My World of Birds: Memoirs of an Ornithologist.
In the course of his research, Wallace became convinced that the mortality of birds on campus and elsewhere was directly related to the use of DDT on trees with Dutch Elm disease. Rachel Carson knew of his research and corresponded with him (unfortunately this correspondence has not survived). Carson respected the work of Wallace and allowed him to read and review the chapter on birds in her indictment of the unregulated use of pesticides Silent Spring.
George J. Wallace died March 8, 1986.
The George John Wallace collection is arranged into the following series: Organizational and Topical files; Correspondence; Pesticides / Michigan Pesticides Council; Writings; Course Materials; and Miscellaneous. Within the organizational files are materials relating to his activities with such groups as the American Ornithologists' Union and the National and Michigan Audubon Society. The topical files concern Wallace's general interest in birds and the study of ornithology. Of some interest are files of documentation collected by Wallace relating to the study of the effect of pesticides on bird populations.
Subjects:
American Ornithologists' Union.; Michigan Audubon Society.; Michigan Pesticides Council.; Michigan State University--Faculty.; Ornithology--Study and teaching.; Pesticides and wildlife.; Pesticides--Environmental aspects.; Wallace, George John, 1906-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Organizational and Topical files
  - American Ornithological Union
    - Conservation Committee (Box 1)
    - Meetings (Box 1)
  - Argonne National Laboratory, 1973-1977; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Aretê Publishing Company (regarding publication of articles on birds), 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Audubon societies
    - Lansing Audubon Society (Box 1)
    - Michigan Audubon Society (Box 1)
    - Michigan Audubon Society (cont.) (Box 2)
    - Massachusetts Audubon Society (Box 2)
    - National Audubon Society (Box 2)
  - Better East Lansing Committee, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Bird banding, 5 folders
    - 1966-1980 (Box 2)
    - 1949-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1965-1985 (Box 2)
    - 1965-1984 (Box 2)
  - Bird collections, 1939-1982; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Bird Control Seminar, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Bird records
    - Michigan, correspondence regarding, 1951-1984 (Box 2)
    - Biological Station, 1958-1960 (Box 2)
    - Christmas counts, 1956-1980 (Box 2)
    - East Lansing campus and vicinity, 1959-1973 (Box 2)
    - Eagle and osprey survey, 1961-1981 (Box 2)
    - TV tower casualties, Lansing, 1959-1967 (Box 2)
  - Birding, 1965-1981 (Box 2)
  - Birds
    - Barn Owl, 3 folders
      - 1945-1947 (Box 2)
      - 1930-1965 (Box 2)
      - 1946-1973 (Box 2)
    - Blue Jay, 1923 (Box 3)
    - Chickadees, 1937-1942 (Box 3)
    - Hawk and Owl, 2 folders
      - 1949 (Box 3)
      - 1947-1954 (Box 3)
    - Kirtland Warbler, 1963-1984 (Box 3)
    - Monk Parakeet, 1971-1974 (Box 3)
    - Pheasant, 1920-1937 (Box 3)
    - Predatory birds, 1941-1942 (Box 3)
    - Thrushes, 1958-1970 (Box 3)
  - Brewer Research Award, 1974-1980 (Box 3)
  - Central Michigan University, 1949-1973 (Box 3)
  - Christmas letters, 1965-1978 (Box 3)
  - Cooper Ornithological Society, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Dutch Elm Disease, 1958-1965 (Box 3)
  - Ecology Discussion Group and related, 1956-1969 (Box 3)
  - Falconry, 1970-1979 (Box 3)
  - Fellowship -- South America, 1954-1961 (Box 3)
  - Hartwick Pines -- birds, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Huron Mountains -- birds, 1960 (Box 3)
  - International Biological Programme, 1965-1968 (Box 3)
  - Kalamazoo Nature Center, 1962-1972 (Box 3)
  - Kellogg Biological Station, 1959-1968 (Box 3)
  - Lectures -- Audubon chapters, 1957-1985 (Box 3)
  - Lectures -- miscellaneous, 1946-1984 (Box 3)
  - Lectures -- pesticides, 1959-1972 (Box 3)
  - Lectures -- radio and television, 1953-1959 (Box 3)
  - Littlefield Edward, 1982-1985 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Association of Conservation Ecologists, 1963-1976 (Box 3)
  - Microphthalmic birds, 1953-1955 (Box 3)
  - Midwest Wildlife Conference, 1948 (Box 3)
  - Myadestes, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
  - National Institute of Health, 1959-1967 (Box 3)
  - National Science Foundation, 1955-1980 (Box 3)
  - Rachel Carson Trust, 1967-1972 (Box 3)
  - Trout Unlimited, 1973-1985 (Box 4)
  - Wells, Carleton, 1946-1985 (Box 4)
  - Who's Who / American Men of Science, undated (Box 4)
  - Wilson Ornithological Club, 2 folders
    - 1941-1974 (Box 4)
    - 1949-1964 (Box 4)
  - World Book Encyclopedia, 1951-1985 (Box 4)
- Correspondence
  - General
    - A-Z, 1936-1943; 5 folders (Box 4)
    - 1941-1943 (Box 4)
      (miscellaneous)
    - 1944-1947 (Box 4)
    - 1948-1950 (Box 4)
    - 1951-1955, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 4)
    - (during sabbatical in Colombia) A-Z, 1955-1957; 5 folders (Box 4)
    - 1964-1971, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - 1970s-1980, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Jack Pine Warbler editor's files
    - A-Z, 1940s-1950s; 7 folders (Box 5)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 5)
  - My World of Birds (fan mail received about GW's book), 1979 (Box 5)
  - Graduate Students
    - Armstrong, William, 1958-1970 (Box 5)
    - Beetley, Bruce, 1967-1976 (Box 5)
    - Bernard, Richard F., 1959-1975 (Box 5)
    - Boykins, Ernest, 1963-1980 (Box 5)
    - Bradfield, Paul L., 1969-1971 (Box 5)
    - Divoky, George, 1967-1972 (Box 5)
    - Duke, Gary, 1966-1977 (Box 5)
    - Eyer, Lester E., 1950-1980 (Box 5)
    - Fleming, Robert L., 1961-1983 (Box 5)
    - Fulk, George W., 1966-1968 (Box 5)
    - Hamel, Paul, 1970-1980 (Box 5)
    - Holcomb, Larry, 1963-1967 (Box 5)
    - Kee, Tom, 1963-1981 (Box 5)
    - Kirkland, Gordon L., 1967-1980 (Box 5)
    - Mahan, Harold, 1958-1970 (Box 5)
    - Mehner, John, 1957-1975 (Box 5)
    - Osborne, David, 1963-1970 (Box 5)
    - Pellerin, George, 1955-1970 (Box 5)
    - Shooks, Wayne, 1967-1969 (Box 5)
    - Smith, C. Roy, 1965-1968 (Box 5)
    - Smith, W. John, 1956-1971 (Box 5)
    - Vanden Berge, James C., 1959-1982 (Box 5)
    - Zimmerman, John, 1957-1967 (Box 5)
- Pesticides / Michigan Pesticide Council
  - Collected information
    - Cereal leaf beetle, 1964 (Box 6)
    - Chemicals (mainly dieldrin use), 1964-1974 (Box 6)
    - Coho salmon and pesticides, 1960-1969 (Box 6)
    - Conferences, seminars, etc. (mainly Michigan Agricultural Pesticide Conference), 1948-1963 (Box 6)
    - Eagles and Ospreys, effect of pesticides, 1964-1974 (Box 6)
    - Egg shells, thinning of, 1970-1972 (Box 6)
    - Fire ant control, 1958-1973 (Box 6)
    - Fish and Wildlife Service (US), Dutch Elm disease control projects of Graduate Assistants
      - Richard F. Bernard, 1958-1962 (Box 6)
      - Paul L. Bradfield, 1965-1972 (Box 6)
    - Gypsy Moth control, 1972-1975 (Box 6)
    - Herbicides, 1960-1975 (Box 6)
    - Hickey / Hunt (correspondence and research papers of Joseph J. Hickey and L. Barrie Hunt), 1958-1968 (Box 6)
    - Japanese beetle and pesticides, 1959-1975 (Box 6)
    - Larson, J. David (president of Normal Soil, Inc.), 1953-1966 (Box 6)
    - Legislation and resolutions
      - General, 1959-1974 (Box 6)
      - HB 3911 (pesticide control in Michigan), 1969 (Box 6)
      - Hearings before the Hart subcommittee on the environment, 1969-1970 (Box 6)
    - Letters to the editor and other writings (manuscript copies), 1958-1960 (Box 6)
    - Mortality of robins and other birds, 1958-1966 (Box 6)
    - Mosquito control, 1963-1975 (Box 6)
    - National Audubon Society, 1960-1972 (Box 6)
    - National Wildlife Federation, 1958-1966 (Box 6)
    - PCBs, 1968-1972 (Box 6)
    - Predatory birds, 1967-1973 (Box 6)
    - Reports and miscellaneous articles, 1958-1974; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Robin census, 1960-1970 (Box 7)
    - Robin study, 1959 (Box 7)
    - Robin survey, 1959 (Box 7)
    - Scientists' Institute for Public Information, 1964 (Box 7)
    - Spraying data, 1959-1965 (Box 7)
    - Water, contamination due to use of pesticides, 1959-1968 (Box 7)
    - Wisconsin, hearings on use of pesticides, 1968-1969 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Pesticide Council
    - Correspondence and material collected for use in MPC newsletter (Box 7)
- Writings
  - Drafts of articles and book reviews (Box 8)
    (unprocessed)
  - Our Berkshires newspaper column, 1940-1942; 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Snowy Egret, 1929-1931 (Box 8)
    (Berrien Springs, Michigan serial publication containing articles by Wallace)
- Course materials
  - MSU classes in zoology and biology (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous
  - Proceedings: George and Martha Wallace vs. Crawford County Road Commission, 1978 (Box 9)
  - Photographs (Box 9)
  - Retirement letters (Box 9)
  - Scrapbooks with clippings from his early career (Box 9)
  - Birds lists, 2 boxes; 1 folders (Box 10)